Guide to the Calla Raynor papers, circa 1950s-1970s UA.29.02.0242
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Calla Raynor papers
1952-1980
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
Raynor, Calla
UA.29.02.0242
6 Linear Feet
Calla Raynor began her career at Duke in the Physical Education department in 1962 and served as the women’s varsity tennis coach from 1967 to 1973. Raynor was instrumental in co-founding Duke University's women's basketball program. This collection contains correspondence, teaching materials, materials related to Ms. Raynor’s education at the Woman’s College of the University of North Carolina (now UNC-Greensboro), UNC-Chapel Hill, and Duke University. The collection also includes sporting event materials, student athlete records, tournament materials, newspaper clippings, audiovisual materials, collegiate sports institutions and organizations for women, and other records from Raynor’s career at Duke.
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
All or portions of this collection may be housed off-site in Duke University's Library Service Center. The library may require up to 48 hours to retrieve these materials for research use.
Please contact Research Services staff before visiting the University Archives to use this collection.
Provenance
Transfer, 2014
Historical Note
Calla Raynor was instrumental in Duke University's physical education program, working as an instructor, a head tennis coach, and co-founder of the women's basketball program.
Calla “Harvey” Raynor attended the Woman’s College of the University of North Carolina (now UNC-Greensboro) during her undergraduate career and studied physical education. She later completed additional coursework at UNC-Chapel Hill and Duke University to expand her knowledge of teaching and physical education.
Raynor began her career at Duke in the Physical Education department in 1962 and served as the women’s varsity tennis coach from 1967 to 1973. Raynor was broadly involved in the athletic department, teaching courses on various physical education, health, and sports subjects. Lorraine Woodyard, the who served as the Head of Women's Athletics beginning in 1972 and eventually in other high-ranking positions, encouraged Raynor to participate and teach in a variety of different sports. Raynor, working with co-coach Lorraine Woodyard, helped found the Duke women’s basketball program in 1968 and held her position as a basketball co-coach until 1973. She became the head of the tennis program in 1973 and led the university to victory in numerous regional and national tournaments. She retired in 2002 and was honored by the Atlantic Coast conference in 2008 as an ACC Women’s Basketball Legend.
Collection Overview
This collection contains correspondence, teaching materials, materials related to Ms. Raynor’s undergraduate coursework at the Woman’s College of the University of North Carolina (now UNC-Greensboro) and graduate coursework at UNC-Chapel Hill, sporting event materials, student athlete records, tournament materials, newspaper clippings, photographs, and other records. Materials are related to Duke University’s sports program, as well as materials from other universities and colleges. The collection includes articles and publications related to physical education instruction, primarily from outside sources. Although Raynor's teaching files are included, such as quizzes and exams, most of the published articles were authored by individuals outside of Duke University.
Sports association materials include materials from the early 1970s to the early 1980s -- these materials include records from the Division of Girls’ and Women’s Sports (DGWS), which became the Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women in 1971.
Related Materials
Athletics Council records, University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Dept. of Athletics Records, University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Athletics Reference collection, University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library
News Service Biographical files, University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Sports Information Office records, University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Tennis records, University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Women’s Basketball records, University Archives, David M. Rubenstein Rare Book and Manuscript Library
Sports for women -- North Carolina -- History; Women coaches (Athletics); Physical education and training -- Curricula; Coaches (Athletics); Tennis; Physical education and training -- North Carolina; Physical education and training -- Study and teaching (Higher) -- United States; College athletes; Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women; Duke University -- Faculty; Duke University -- Basketball; Duke University -- Athletics; Atlantic Coast Conference; Raynor, Calla; Duke University. Women's Dept. of Physical Education
- Teaching materials, early 1960s - 1974 and undated
  Scope and Contents
  Series includes materials related to Calla Raynor’s teaching career at Duke for a variety of physical education courses, including: syllabi, exams, quizzes, grading rubrics and answer keys, copies of articles, and drawings/diagrams of various sports.
  - American Heart Association life Support test (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Anatomy and Biology test sheets (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Archery (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Arts and Crafts, 1966 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Assorted Sports (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Badminton (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Basketball (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Bibliographies (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Bowling (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Conditioning (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Dance (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Fencing (Box 1, Folder 12)
  - General papers (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Golf (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Gymnastics (Box 1, Folder 15)
  - Hockey (Box 1, Folder 16)
  - Posture (Box 1, Folder 17)
  - Soccer (Box 1, Folder 18)
  - Softball (Box 1, Folder 19)
  - Square Dance (Box 1, Folder 20)
  - Student papers (Box 1, Folder 21)
  - Stunts (Box 1, Folder 22)
  - Swimming (Box 1, Folder 23)
  - Table Tennis (Box 1, Folder 24)
  - Tennis (Box 1, Folder 25)
  - Tennis (Box 1, Folder 26)
  - Track and Field (Box 1, Folder 27)
  - Various tests (Box 1, Folder 28)
  - Volleyball (Box 1, Folder 29)
- Student materials, 1952-1966 and undated
  Series includes materials related to Calla Raynor’s academic career, primarily at the Woman’s College of the University of North Carolina (now UNC-Greensboro), and related to instruction in teaching and physical education. Materials from UNC-Chapel Hill and Duke University are also included. The series also includes audiovisual materials – including personal slides from Ms. Raynor’s academic career at the Woman’s College of the University of North Carolina (now UNC-Greensboro), primarily reflecting her dorm life.
  - Anatomy 22 (Box 1, Folder 30)
  - Biology 102, 1958 (Box 1, Folder 31)
  - Biology 271, 1953 (Box 1, Folder 32)
  - Conditioning Notebooks (Box 1, Folder 33)
  - Conduct of U.S. Physical Education Programs (Box 1, Folder 34)
  - Education 135, 1964 (Box 1, Folder 35)
  - Education 202 (Box 1, Folder 36)
  - Education 317, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 37)
  - Education 350 (Box 1, Folder 38)
  - Folk Dance (Box 1, Folder 39)
  - Golf, lesson plans (Box 1, Folder 40)
  - The Good Ship, C.B., undated (Box 1, Folder 41)
  - General student notebooks, undated (Box 1, Folder 42)
  - Greensboro Parks and Recreation field trip (Box 1, Folder 43)
  - Health 123 (Box 1, Folder 44)
  - Health 367, 1960 (Box 1, Folder 45)
  - History 102, 1959 (Box 2, Folder 46)
  - Health and Physical Education -- Greensboro Public Schools (Box 2, Folder 47)
  - Intramurals term papers, 1966 (Box 2, Folder 48)
  - Kinesiology (Box 2, Folder 49)
  - Lesson plans and student teaching materials, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 50)
  - Miscellaneous essays, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 51)
  - Modern Dance (Box 2, Folder 52)
  - Physical Education 121 (Box 2, Folder 53)
  - Physical Education 126 (Box 2, Folder 54)
  - Physical Education 127 (Box 2, Folder 55)
  - Physical Education 221 (Box 2, Folder 56)
  - Physical Education 241 (Box 2, Folder 57)
  - Physical Education 351 (Box 2, Folder 58)
  - Physical Education 352 (Box 2, Folder 59)
  - Physical Education 360 (Box 2, Folder 60)
  - Physical Education 461 (Box 2, Folder 61)
  - Physical Education 464 (Box 2, Folder 62)
  - Physical Education 465 (Box 2, Folder 63)
  - Physical Education 469 (Box 2, Folder 64)
  - Physical Education 523 (Box 2, Folder 65)
  - Physical Education, N.C. Public Schools, 1952 (Box 2, Folder 66)
  - Physiology 1L (Box 2, Folder 67)
  - Recreation 176-177 (Box 2, Folder 68)
  - Red Cross, Canoe Storage (Box 2, Folder 69)
  - Sociology 212 (Box 2, Folder 70)
  - Sociology 335 (Box 2, Folder 71)
  - Softball 360 (Box 2, Folder 72)
  - Student teaching materials -- various (Box 2, Folder 73)
  - Student notebook, 1 (Box 5, Folder 74)
  - Student notebook, 2 (Box 5, Folder 75)
  - Student's workbook -- Introduction to Psychology (Box 2, Folder 76)
  - Tests and measurements (Box 2, Folder 77)
  - Track and Field (Box 2, Folder 78)
  - UNCG Woman's College, Intramural activities (Box 2, Folder 79)
  - UNCG Woman's College, notebook 1 (Box 2, Folder 80)
  - UNCG Woman's College, notebook 2 (Box 2, Folder 81)
  - UNCG Woman's College, Tennis Club constitution (Box 2, Folder 82)
  - Volleyball officials, 1961 (Box 2, Folder 83)
  - Slides, 1961 (Box 4, Folder 157)
- Correspondence, 1962-1980 and undated
  Series includes ingoing and outgoing correspondence from 1962-1980. Correspondence is primarily related to athletics -- including correspondence with tennis players, other university coaches, and athletic departments to organize tennis tournaments.
  - Coaches, 1978-1979 (Box 2, Folder 84)
  - General correspondence, 1962-1975 (Box 2, Folder 85)
  - General correspondence, 1976-1980 (Box 2, Folder 86)
  - Players, 1965-1975 (Box 3, Folder 87)
  - Players, 1976-1977 (Box 3, Folder 88)
- Events, 1964-1980 and undated
  Series includes correspondence, publicity materials and event pamphlets, tournament scoring sheets and brackets, and travel information. The majority of events are from national or regional tennis tournaments in which Duke University participated, including NCAA tournaments, NCAIAW and AIAW tournaments, and regional tournaments such as the Lady Seminole Invitational Tournament, among others.
  - ACC Women's Tennis Tournament, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 89)
  - ACC Women's Tennis Tournament, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 90)
  - ACC Women's Tennis Tournament, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 91)
  - AIAW Natinal Small College Invitational Tennis Tournament, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 92)
  - AIAW National Tennis Championships, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 93)
  - AIAW National Tennis Championships, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 94)
  - AIAW Southern Region II Tournament, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 95)
  - AIAW Southern Region II Tournament, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 96)
  - Carolina's AAU Championships, 1964 (Box 3, Folder 97)
  - Lady Seminole 12th Annual Invitational, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 98)
  - Lady Seminole 13th Annual Invitational, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 99)
  - Lady Seminole 14th Annual Invitational, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 100)
  - Lady Seminole 16th Annual Invitational, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 101)
  - Lady Seminole 17th Annual Invitational, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 102)
  - NCAIAW Tennis Tournament, 1974 (Box 3, Folder 103)
  - NCAIAW Tennis Tournament, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 104)
  - NCAIAW Tennis Tournament, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 105)
  - NCAIAW Tennis Tournament, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 106)
  - NCAIAW Tennis Tournament, 1979 (Box 3, Folder 107)
  - NCAIAW Tennis Tournament, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 108)
  - NCAIAW Volleyball Tournament, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 109)
  - NCAIAW Volleyball Tournament, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 110)
  - University of Virginia Invitational Tennis Tournament, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 111)
  - USTA Women's National Tennis Championships, 1975 (Box 3, Folder 112)
  - USTA Women's National Tennis Championships, 1976 (Box 3, Folder 113)
- Articles and publications, 1958-1978 and undated
  Series includes materials related to athletics -- including pamphlets from Duke University and other institutions, newspaper and article clippings, press releases, and newsletters. Included are publications from the Woman’s College of the University of North Carolina (UNC-Greensboro), such as The Major’s Voice, a publication of the Physical Education Department.
  The majority of publications are not authored by Raynor -- many are scholarly publications designed to help in physical education instruction, as well as publications of Duke University. The series also includes materials from UNC-Greensboro's Physical Education Department, to which Raynor contributed.
  - Articles and newspaper clippings, 1958-1975 and undated (Box 3, Folder 114)
  - Humorous materials, undated (Box 3, Folder 115)
  - Journal of National Institute on Girls Sports, 1965 (Box 3, Folder 116)
  - The Major's Voice, 1958-1960 (Box 3, Folder 117)
  - Newsletters, 1975-1977 (Box 3, Folder 118)
  - Pamphlets, 1964-1976 and undated (Box 3, Folder 119)
  - Press releases, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 120)
  - Unpublished materials (Box 3, Folder 121)
  - Woman's Day, May 1964 (Box 3, Folder 122)
- Committees and organizations, 1964-1980 and undated
  Series includes correspondence, meeting minutes, convention materials, and handbooks and other publications related to both national and regional sports organizations. Major bodies include the National Collegiate Athletic Association (NCAA), the Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (AIAW), which was preceded by the Division for Girls’ and Women’s Sports (DGWS). Materials are primarily from the mid-1960s to the 1980s.
  - Association for Intercollegiate Athletics for Women (AIAW) administrative files (Box 3, Folder 123)
  - AIAW Delegate Assembly, 1973 (Box 3, Folder 124)
  - AIAW Delegate Assembly, 1977 (Box 3, Folder 125)
  - AIAW Delegate Assembly, 1978 (Box 3, Folder 126)
  - AIAW Delegate Assembly, 1980 (Box 3, Folder 127)
  - AIAW directory, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 128)
  - AIAW handbook, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 129)
  - AIAW Letters of Intent, 1977-1978 (Box 3, Folder 130)
  - AIAW membership reports and rosters, 1977-1978 (Box 4, Folder 131)
  - Athletic and Recreation Fedration of College Women (ARFCW) materials, 1965-1967 and undated (Box 4, Folder 132)
  - DGWS National Coaches Conference, 1973 (Box 4, Folder 133)
  - NCAA 73rd Annual Convention, 1979 (Box 4, Folder 134)
  - North Carolina Association for Health, Physical Education and Recreation (NCAHPER) Convention, 1965 (Box 4, Folder 135)
  - NCAHPER meeting, 1958 (Box 4, Folder 136)
  - NCAIAW Executive Council, 1973-1975 (Box 4, Folder 137)
  - NCAIAW general session, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 138)
  - NCAIAW state handbook, 1976-1977 (Box 4, Folder 139)
  - Various summer camp materials, 1964-1967 and undated (Box 4, Folder 140)
- Administrative files, 1962-1980 and undated
  Series includes materials related to Calla Raynor’s personal administration of athletics at Duke University, Duke University administration and Duke Athletics administration, and various tennis forms and reports.
  - Admissions tracking reports, 1976 (Box 4, Folder 141)
  - Athletic awards, 1976 and undated (Box 4, Folder 142)
  - Calendars and planners, 1978-1979 (Box 4, Folder 143)
  - Duke Athletics, circa 1975-1979 (Box 4, Folder 144)
  - Duke University administration files, 1973-1977 and undated (Box 4, Folder 145)
  - Physical Education class schedules, 1962-1968 (Box 4, Folder 146)
  - Resumes, Calla Raynor, 1962-1979 (Box 4, Folder 147)
  - Tennis budgets, 1977-1981 (Box 4, Folder 148)
  - Tennis eligibility forms, 1975-1980 (Box 4, Folder 149)
  - Tennis match agreements, 1975-1980 (Box 4, Folder 150)
  - Tennis player match records, 1977 (Box 4, Folder 151)
  - Tennis report, 1974-1975 (Box 4, Folder 152)
  - Tennis rosters, 1976-1978 (Box 4, Folder 153)
  - Tennis schedules, 1971-1979 and undated (Box 4, Folder 154)
  - Travel forms, 1975 and undated (Box 4, Folder 155)
  - WRA bicycle rental, 1971-1979 and undated (Box 4, Folder 156)